Margaret Casey Gates
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Margaret Casey Gates papers
1934-1988
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Gates, Margaret Casey
1.0 linear foot
The papers of Washington, D.C. painter Margaret Casey Gates date from 1934-1988, and measure 1.0 linear foot. Gates' papers document her work as a painter, her projects for the New Deal federal arts programs, the Phillips Memorial Gallery and its art school, where she attended school and later worked as secretary and where her husband Robert Franklin Gates was a teacher, and the Washington, D.C. arts scene. Found are scattered correspondence, seven sketchbooks by Gates and two sketchbooks of her divorced husband Robert Franklin Gates. Miscellaneous notes and writings, a scrapbook, printed material, and photographs of Gates, her husband, friends, artwork, and views of the Virgin Islands are also included in the papers.
Provenance
The Margaret Casey Gates papers were a bequest from Gates' estate in 1994, executed by her niece Joyce D. Svedberg.
Related Material
Also found in the Archives of American Art are the papers of Gates' divorced husband Robert Franklin Gates dating from 1910-1988.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Margaret Casey was born in 1903 in the Georgetown section of Washington, D.C. She studied art in the studio of Bertha Perry, and from 1924 to 1926 at the Corcoran Art School. She later studied under Henry Varnum Poor at the Colorado Springs Fine Arts Center.
After working as a commercial artist from 1928-1929, Casey began studying at the Phillips Memorial Gallery in 1931 under C. Law Watkins. There, she met her husband, painter Robert Franklin Gates, and married on January 7, 1933. Robert Franklin Gates (1906-1982), who came to Washington, D.C. in 1930, also studied at the Phillips Gallery Art School and worked with Karl Knaths between 1934 and 1947.
Between 1934 and 1941, Robert Gates, with other artists including Mitchell Jamieson and Prentiss Taylor, made several painting trips to the Virgin Islands on a fine arts commission from the U. S. Treasury Department. Margaret Gates accompanied her husband and produced artwork of her own. She also documented their travels. During this same time, Robert taught at the Phillips Gallery Art School and Margaret was employed as the Art School's secretary. In 1937, they purchased a house in McLean, Virginia where Margaret lived until 1980.
In 1939, Margaret Gates won honorable mention in a national mural competition held by the Section of Fine Arts of the U. S. Public Buildings Administration and was subsequently commissioned by the Federal Works Agency to execute a mural for the Post office at Mebane, North Carolina. The mural was completed and installed in 1941.
During the late 1940s and early 1950s, Margaret Gates wrote articles on art for Washington, D. C. publications including the column "The People vs. Art" for American University's Right Angle, and for the magazine The Washington Spectator.
Margaret and Robert Gates were divorced circa 1955. They had no children.
Margaret Gates exhibited her work in the first exhibition at the National Gallery of Art in 1941, as one of many winners of a national competition sponsored by the Federal Works Agency for artwork to decorate a Marine hospital for lepers in Louisiana. She also exhibited in the "Group Show of Washington Painters" at the Bignou Gallery in New York City, as well as at the Corcoran Gallery of Art, the Philips Collection, the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, the Cincinnati Art Museum, and the Baltimore Museum of Art. A retrospective of her work was exhibited at the Watkins Gallery of American University in 1981. Several of her paintings are in the collection of the Phillips Gallery.
Margaret Casey Gates died on November 4, 1989, in Mitchellville, Maryland.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Washington, D.C. painter Margaret Casey Gates date from 1934-1988, and measure 1.0 linear foot. Gates' papers document her work as a painter, her projects for the New Deal federal arts programs, the Phillips Memorial Gallery and its art school, where she attended school and later worked as secretary and where her husband Robert Franklin Gates was a teacher, and the Washington, D.C. arts scene. Found are scattered correspondence, seven sketchbooks by Gates and two sketchbooks of her divorced husband Robert Franklin Gates. Miscellaneous notes and writings, a scrapbook, printed material, and photographs of Gates, her husband, friends, artwork, and views of the Virgin Islands are also included in the papers.
Twelve folders of scattered correspondence include letters from the Federal Works Agency and one or two letters each from friends and individuals that reflect Gates' wide range of interests and activities. Correspondents include Betty Jean Clark, Arthur G. Dove, D. R. Fitzpatrick, Alice Garrett, John Gernand, Karl Knaths, John L. Lewis, a Brazilian artist named Portinari, Julian Lee Rayford, Alfred Stieglitz, and Prentiss Taylor.
Artwork consists of seven of Margaret Casey Gates' sketchbooks and two of Robert Franklin Gates' sketchbooks of both abstract and figural sketches. Margaret's sketchbooks contain landscapes that illustrate her travels to Colorado, Florida, Maine, Maryland, Utah, Virginia, West Virginia, and the Virgin Islands. Sketchbook #2 contains pencil, ink, and pastel drawings of St. Thomas in the Virgin Islands and an intimate drawing of Robert Franklin Gates, Mitchell Jamieson, and Prentiss Taylor asleep on a ship. Artwork also includes a fine caricature of Robert Franklin Gates by Karl Knaths.
Notes and writings primarily consist of scattered notes and brief descriptive accounts of Gates's experiences at the Phillips Gallery, and at the Colorado Springs Art Center. Her extensive descriptions of her travels to the Virgin Islands are also illustrated.
A scrapbook primarily contains clippings, but also includes an award certificate, letters concerning various topics including Pepsi-Cola's annual art competition and Federal Works Agency projects, brochures for the Phillips Gallery Art School and for the McLean Art Club, and a photograph of the mural at the Mebane, North Carolina post office.
Printed material consists of clippings including copies of the rare magazines The Washington Spectator and the American University publication Right Angle, announcements and catalogs for exhibitions of Gates's work, and miscellaneous booklets and brochures. There is also printed material concerning the Armory Show including a copy of the booklet The Story of the Armory Show by Walt Kuhn.
Photographs are of Margaret Casey Gates, Robert Franklin Gates, friends including Prentiss Taylor, her home, and her artwork. Photographs of Margaret and Robert Gates and their artist friends during their visits to the Virgin Islands in the 1930s are of primary interest, offering unique glimpses of that culture during the 1930s. These photographs include aerial photographs of St. Thomas and photographs by Prentiss Taylor.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 6 series. Each series is arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1934-1986 (Box 1; 12 folders)
Series 2: Artwork, 1935-1965 (Box 1; 12 folders)
Series 3: Notes and Writings, 1939-1984 (Box 1; 7 folders)
Series 4: Scrapbook, 1938-1961 (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1935-1988 (Box 1; 20 folders)
Series 6: Photographs, 1934-1976 (Box 1; 19 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Gates, Robert Franklin,1906-1982; Federal Art Project; Phillips Collection; Phillips Memorial Gallery. Art School;; Armory Show (1913: New York, N.Y.)
Subjects-Topical:
Art, Modern -- 20th century -- Washington (D.C.); Art teachers -- Washington (D.C.); Women painters -- Washington (D.C.); New Deal, 1933-1939; Post office buildings -- North Carolina; Painters -- Washington (D.C.)
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Writings
Names:
Clark, Betty Jean; Dove, Arthur Garfield, 1880-1946; Garrett, Alice Warder; Fitzpatrick, Daniel Robert, 1891-1969; Gates, Robert Franklin, 1906-1982; Gernand, John, 1913-1990; Knaths, Karl, 1891-; Lewis, John L.; Rayford, Julian Lee; Stieglitz, Alfred, 1864-1946; Taylor, Prentiss, 1907-; Federal Works Agency
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Correspondence, 1934-1986, Series 1:; (Box 1; 12 folders)
  Correspondence consists of scattered letters concerning art-related activities including letters from the Federal Works Agency enclosing a contract for the post office mural in Mebane, North Carolina. There are also one or two letters from Betty Jean Clark, Arthur G. Dove, D. R. Fitzpatrick, Alice Garrett, John Gernand, Karl Knaths, John L. Lewis, a Brazilian artist named Portinari, Julian Lee Rayford, Alfred Stieglitz, and Prentiss Taylor.
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1940, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Correspondence, 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Artwork, 1935-1965, Series 2:; (Box 1; 12 folders)
  Seven sketchbooks by Margaret Casey Gates are of landscapes from travels in Colorado, Florida, Maine, Maryland, Utah, Virginia, West Virginia, and the Virgin Islands. Sketchbook #2 contains drawings of St. Thomas in the Virgin Islands and of Robert Franklin Gates, Mitchell Jamieson, and Prentiss Taylor asleep on a ship. There are two sketchbooks by Robert Franklin Gates of figural and abstract studies. There is also a caricature of Robert Franklin Gates by Karl Knaths.
  - Sketchbook 1 by Margaret Casey Gates, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sketchbook 2 by Margaret Casey Gates, 1935-1940, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Sketchbook 3 by Margaret Casey Gates, 1938-1948 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Sketchbook 4 by Margaret Casey Gates, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sketchbook 5 by Margaret Casey Gates, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Sketchbook 6 by Margaret Casey Gates, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Sketchbook 7 by Margaret Casey Gates, 1949-1965, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - Sketchbook by Robert Franklin Gates, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Sketchbook by Robert Franklin Gates, 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Caricature Drawing of Robert Franklin Gates by Karl Knaths, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Notes and Writings, 1939-1984, Series 3:; (Box 1; 7 folders)
  Notes and writings primarily consist of descriptive accounts of Gates's experiences at the Phillips Gallery, at the Colorado Springs Art Center, and of her travels to the Virgin Islands in the 1930s. Some of the writings are also illustrated.
  - List of Groceries and Household Items, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Notes about Early Days at the Phillips Gallery, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Typescript Describing Margaret Casey Gates's Approach to Painting, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Typescript "The Future of Evolution," undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Manuscript "The Amateur Traveler at St. Thomas, or Facts and Fancies About the Virgin Islands," 1936 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Typescript about Colorado Springs Art Center, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Writings by Others, "Dedication of Woodcarving for the Lewinsville Retirement Residence," 1984 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Scrapbook, 1938-1961, Series 4:; (Box 1; 3 folders)
  The scrapbook contains an award certificate, letters concerning various topics including Pepsi-Cola's annual art competition and Federal Works Agency projects, clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, brochures for the Phillips Gallery Art School and for the McLean Art Club, and a photograph of the mural at the Mebane, North Carolina post office.
  - Scrapbook, 1938-1961, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 32-34)
- Printed Material, 1935-1988, Series 5:; (Box 1; 20 folders)
  Printed material consists of clippings including copies of the rare magazines The Washington Spectator and the American University publication Right Angle, announcements and catalogs for exhibitions of Gates's work, and miscellaneous booklets and brochures. There is also printed material concerning the Armory Show including a copy of the booklet The Story of the Armory Show by Walt Kuhn.
  - Clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Clippings, 1936-1949 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Clippings, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Clippings, 1955-1966 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Clippings, 1968-1979 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Clippings, 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Clippings, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Clippings, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1953-1981 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Robert Franklin Gates and for Sarah Baker, 1976-1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Printed Material Concerning the Armory Show, 1938-1988 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Booklet American Paintings - Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Brochures for the Phillips Gallery Art School, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Travel Brochures for Key West and the Virgin Islands, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Picture Postcards, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1946-1988 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Photographs, 1934-1976, Series 6:; (Box 1; 19 folders)
  Photographs are of Margaret Casey Gates, Robert Franklin Gates, friends including Prentiss Taylor, Gates' home, and artwork. There are also photographs of various views of the Virgin Islands in the 1930s including aerial photographs of St. Thomas, and photographs by Prentiss Taylor.
  - Photographs of Margaret Casey Gates, 1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Photographs of Robert Franklin Gates, 1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Photographs of Margaret and Robert Gates, 1951, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 57-59)
  - Photographs of Margaret and Robert Gates with Friends in the Virgin Islands, 1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Friends, 1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Photographs of the Virgin Islands by Prentiss Taylor, undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Photographs of St. Croix, Virgin Islands, undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs of the Virgin Islands, undated, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 64-67)
  - Photographs of McLean, Virginia, Residence, undated (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Photographs of the Washington, D. C. Area, 1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Locations, 1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Margaret Casey Gates, 1976, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 71-72)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 73)